<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Parliaments censvre on Sir Richard Gvrney, Lord Major of the honourable city of London, August 12, 1642 with the articles of his impeachment, wherein he stood charged of many offences, crimes and high misdemeanors committed by the said Sir Richard Gurney during the time of his majoralty.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B22187</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12248633</idno>
  <idno type="VID">197466</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240961237</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2132</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12248633</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B22187)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 197466)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 246:E111, no 6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Parliaments censvre on Sir Richard Gvrney, Lord Major of the honourable city of London, August 12, 1642 with the articles of his impeachment, wherein he stood charged of many offences, crimes and high misdemeanors committed by the said Sir Richard Gurney during the time of his majoralty.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Cave,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>August 13, 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Gurney, Richard, --  Sir, 1577-1647.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Impeachments --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:197466:1"/>
            <p>The Parliaments CENSVRE ON Sir RICHARD GVRNEY, Lord Major of the Honourable City of LONDON <hi>August</hi> 12. 1642.</p>
            <p>WITH The Articles of His Impeachment, wherein He stood charged of many offences, crimes, and high misdemeanors, committed by the said Sir <hi>Richard Gurney,</hi> during the time of his Majoralty.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Tudor rose surmounted by a crown</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Scottish thistle surmounted by a crown</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Irish harp surmounted by a crown</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>French fleur-de-lis surmounted by a crown</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for <hi>Iohn Cave. August</hi> 13. 1642.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:197466:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles_of_impeachment">
            <pb facs="tcp:197466:2"/>
            <head>The Impeachment of the House of Commons against Sir <hi>Richard Gurney,</hi> Knight and Baronet, Lord Major of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irst,</hi> That the said Sir <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Gurney</hi> being nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, elected, and chosen Lord Major of the said Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>London</hi> for this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent year 1642. and in the year of our Soveraign Lord King <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> the eighteenth; Whereby the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering rule and Government of the said City of <hi>London,</hi> was committed to the trust care and charge of him the said Sir <hi>Richard Gurney;</hi> He the said Sir <hi>Richard Gurney</hi> in or about the Month of <hi>Iune</hi> last past, and during the time of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joralty
<pb facs="tcp:197466:3"/> as aforesaid, in contempt and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice against the Parliament, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings thereof, and contrary to his Oath and the faith and trust reposed in him; and with an intent purpose and resolution, to overthrow the ancient Customes and Usages of the said Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and with an intent, purpose and resolution, to bring in an arbitrary and tyrannicall Government; contrary to the Lawes and Statutes of this Realm, and the setled Government established in the same Kingdom: And with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and endeavour to levie War against the Parliament, did in or about the Month of <hi>June</hi> last past, proclaim and publish, or did cause and procure to be openly read, published, and published, within the said City of <hi>London</hi> and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs of the same, divers illegall Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, containnig in them matter of dangerous consequence, contrary to the Votes and Orders of both Houses of Parliament, and likewise contrary to the Rights and Priviledges there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb facs="tcp:197466:3"/> and the Liberty and Propriety of the Subject.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> that where in or about the moneth of <hi>December</hi> last past a great number of his Maiesties dutyfull and Loyall Subiects in and about the citie of <hi>London</hi> did contrive and draw up a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Petition wherein was contained ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their grievances with an intent to present the same to the Honourabe House, he the said Sir <hi>Richard Gurney</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then and now Lord Maior of <hi>London</hi> did earnestly labour and endeavour to suppresse the said Petition and to hinder the same from being delivered to this Honourable House, and did menace and threaten the said Petitioners; and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned divers of them contrary to the laws and Statutes of this Realm and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the liberty of the Subiect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:197466:4"/>
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the said Sir <hi>Richard Gurney,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with one <hi>Binyon</hi> did further plot and contrive one seditious and scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Petition, containing matters of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous consequence, endeavouring there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to raise tumults and discords within the said City, and to make and increase the difference between His Majestie and the Parliament, whereupon many inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent persons, ill-affected to the State, and the proceedings of Parliament, did in a riatous and unlawfull manner assemble and gather themselves together in <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side,</hi> within the said Citie; and then and there committed many riotous acts, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Peace of our Soveraign Lord the King, and contrary to the civill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the said Citie. And he the said Sir <hi>Richard Gurney,</hi> did purposely, wittingly, and willingly, permit and suffer the aforesaid riotous persons, to escape without due and deserved punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:197466:4"/>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That whereas by Order of both Houses of <hi>Parliament,</hi> the said Lord Major was appointed to call a Common Councell, he refused so to do; and when a Common Councell was called by the said Sir <hi>Richard Gurney,</hi> it was moved on the behalf of both Houses of <hi>Parliament,</hi> that great quantity of Armes and other Ammunition, should be said into some, Store-houses within the said City for His Majesties service, and the good and safety of the Kingdom, he the said Sir <hi>Richard Gurney</hi> being ill affected to the State▪ and the proceedings of Parliament, did in a most obstinate and malicious manner withstand, refuse, or gainsay the s<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> contrary to the Order of both Houses of Parliament, giving many insolent spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches against the Authoritie thereof, with an intent and pur<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ose to discourage all well-affected persons, to yeild obedience to the Orders of Parliament, and to make difference and division between his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty
<pb facs="tcp:197466:5"/> and the Parliament. <hi>All which mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and things have been perpetrated, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and done by him, the said Sir</hi> Richard Gurney, <hi>during the time of his Majoraltie aforesaid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="censure">
            <head>The Censure of the Lord Major <date>the 12. of <hi>August.</hi> 1642.</date>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>I. That the said Lord Maior shall not be capable to beare any Office of Honour or trust in the Common-wealth.</item>
               <item>II. That he shall be degraded of all his Honours and Titles.</item>
               <item>III. That he shall continue Prisoner in the Tower, during the pleasure of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>